《波洛探案集》第一季第10集
主演：大卫·苏切特
《噩梦》
百代新闻
Pathe Gazette 是英国百代1910至1970年间制作的新闻影片
法利食品\n厂区入口
屠宰场
入口
英国馅饼世界知名
British pies are famous the world over,
法利食品去年的馅饼产量达五百万个
and last year, Farley's Foods produced five million of them,
从牛肉腰花馅饼
everything from steak-and-kidney
到菜肉烘饼 应有尽有
to Cornish pasties.
但是老法利并不满足
But that's not enough for old man Farley.
他想要产量翻番
He wants to double the score.
在新的厂房里
Work's been pushing ahead
生产在不断扩大
on the new extension to his factory,
本周法利食品迎来了重要的一天
and this week, the great day dawns.
我的朋友们
My friends --
希望我们可以以朋友相称
I hope I may call you my friends.
我付给你们工钱
After all, I pay your wages.
1935年 我们的馅饼销量
In 1935, we sold more pies
比以往任何时期都要高
than at any time in our history.
然而你们中的一些人 他们带着某种政治目的
Yet there are those among you, politically motivated,
仍在批评你们做得不够好
who still try to say that you are not doing well.
不要听信他们
Don't listen to them.
现在让我们说些高兴的事
And now let us move on to happier things.
今天 我再次站在这里
Once more I stand before you here
庆祝我们伟大企业的新厂投产
to open yet another new wing of our great enterprise.
乔安娜
Joanna.
昨天怎么没给我打电话?
Why didn't you call me yesterday?
你不应该来这
You mustn't come here.
我想见你
I've got to see you.
乔安娜 这样不好
It's no good, Joanna.
为什么? 你想说什么?
What isn't? What do you mean?
他们通知我两周后离职
I've been given two weeks' notice.
是我父亲的意思?
By my father?
呃 是的 虽然不是他亲自说的
Well, not directly, but, yes.
为什么?
Why?
显然 他发现了我们之间的事
Because he's found out about us, of course.
我得走了
I've got to go.
天啊
Oh, God.
我一直认为 这是一种合作关系
"I'd like to think that it's been a partnership,
是法利一家与
a partnership between the Farley family
我们这些卑微市民的合作关系
and we humble mortals in the municipality."
工作多得是 赫伯特
There are other jobs, Herbert.
可是有你父亲对我的糟糕评价
Not with your father's bad opinion following me
就不好说了
wherever I go.
我真想杀了他
I could kill him!
我真的想杀了他
I could really kill him!
说这些也无济于事
Talking like that doesn't do any good.
现在 我很荣幸地宣布
A-And now it gives me great pleasure
新厂正式开工
to declare this new wing well and truly open.
见鬼
Bother.
"您的机会来了"
"This is your chance."
你说什么?
What?
"现在是购买真皮皮鞋的好时机
"This is your chance to invest in a pair
一种居家真皮皮鞋"
of Home Phit real leather shoes."
哈 有意思
Oh, that's clever.
把fit的f写成了ph
"Fit" spelled with a "P-H."
"只需寄回这张纸
"Just return this card,
我们的工作人员就会与您联系"
and our representatives will call on you."
很明显 这是定制皮鞋
Made-to-measure shoes, apparently.
看上去很划算啊
Seem awfully reasonable.
不知道他们那有没有定制的
Don't suppose they have any made-to-measure typewriters
打字机啊
in there, have they?
什么?
Sorry?
去年的复活节之后
Ever since last Easter,
我就一直请波洛先生买一台新打字机
I've been asking Mr. Poirot for a new typewriter.
他倒不是吝啬 但是活得有点过于精细
Mr. Poirot isn't mean, but he is careful.
他搬进来的时候发现了这台打印机
He found this typewriter in the flat when he moved in.
以前的人留下的
Someone had left it.
还蛮好用嘛
Jolly useful.
嗯
Hmm.
谁是本尼迪克特·法利?
Who's Benedict Farley?
不知道
No idea.
哦 是法利馅饼厂的那个法利么?
Oh, isn't he Farley's pies?
馅饼厂?
Pies?
怎么了?
Why?
尊敬的先生 本尼迪克特·法利先生
"Dear sir, Mr. Benedict Farley
希望聆听您的建议
would like to have the benefit of your advice.
如您明天方便登门
If convenient to yourself,
他将十分高兴
he would be glad if you would call upon him
地址见上
at the above address
明(周四)晚9点半 恭候光临
at 9:30 tomorrow, Thursday evening.
您忠诚的 雨果·康沃西 秘书
Yours truly, Hugo Cornworthy, Secretary.
附言 来访时请携带此信
P.S. Please bring this letter with you."
麻烦你重复一遍 黑斯廷斯
Repeat that, if you please, Hastings.
尊敬的先生...
"Dear sir --"
不 不 不
No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
就附言部分
Just the postscript.
附言 来访时请携带此信
"P.S. Please bring this letter with you."
为什么?
Why?
为什么 黑斯廷斯?
Why, Hastings?
真是一封有趣的信
An interesting letter.
是么?
Is it?
我觉得很无聊啊
I thought it was rather dull.
莱蒙小姐说法利先生是做馅饼的
Miss Lemon says he makes pies.
做馅饼的?
Makes pies?
把食品大亨法利说成做馅饼的
Hastings, to say that Benedict Farley makes pies
就好比把瓦格纳说成三流作曲家一样
is like saying that Wagner wrote semiquavers.
味道还不错吧?
They're good pies, are they?
不 糟透了 但确实很畅销
No, horrible, but there are a great many of them.
我猜那是本尼迪克特·法利的命
The fonts and oracle of Benedict Farley's wealth, I surmise, eh?
还有那栋楼
And that, Hastings,
是他做香肠 馅饼和火腿的地方
is where he makes his sausages, his pies, his hams.
住在工厂顶层倒是很方便
Useful, eh, living above the shop?
我猜法利喜欢在这里盯着他的工人
I suppose from here Farley likes to keep an eye on his employees.
千真万确 但可惜的是
No doubt, but it is a pity that such diligence
这并没有改善他所谓的"美食"的口味
does not improve the quality of his so-called delectables.
晚上好
Good evening.
晚上好 先生
Good evening, sir.
波洛先生和黑斯廷斯上尉来拜访法利先生
M. Poirot and Captain Hastings to see Mr. Farley.
很抱歉 先生们
I'm sorry, sir.
只有一个人能进去
I was instructed to admit only one.
这是什么话?
Oh, come, now.
法利先生特别嘱咐只见一位
I was instructed most positively, sir.
十分抱歉
I'm sorry.
这样太不方便了
You know, this is most inconvenient.
抱歉 主人吩咐我看一下邀请信
You'll excuse me, sir. I was told to ask for a letter.
什么?
Pardon?
啊 那封信...
Oh, yes, uh...
在这呢
Ah.
可以了 先生
Thank you, sir.
进来吧
Yeah?
先生 您约的人到了
The gentleman you are expecting, sir.
啊
Oh.
你就是赫尔克里·波洛?
You're Hercule Poirot, eh?
正是我 先生
Monsieur.
坐吧
Sit down.
坐下吧
谢谢 先生
Merci, m-monsieur.
法利先生 有什么可以为您效劳的么?
What is it that you wish to consult me about, M. Farley?
我一直在做同一个梦 夜夜相同
I have the same dream, night after night.
我坐在隔壁自己的书房里
I'm sitting in my room next to this,
在写字台前办公
sitting at my desk, writing.
房间里有个钟
There's a clock in there.
我抬起头
I look up at it.
看到了时间
I see the time.
正好是12点28分
It is exactly 28 minutes past 12:00,
每次都是同样的时间
always the same time.
明白吗?
You understand?
每当看到那个时间 我就知道我要行动了
When I see that time, Poirot, I know I've got to do it.
12点28分
At 28 minutes past 12:00,
我拉开写字台右手第二个抽屉
I open the second drawer down on the right of my desk.
拿出一把左轮手枪
I take out a revolver,
装上子弹
I load it,
然后我走到窗前
and I go over to the window.
接下来呢?
And then?
我自杀了
I shoot myself.
我举起枪
I just lift the gun to my head
然后扣动了扳机
and shoot myself.
你对此怎么看?
What do you make of that?
我已经咨询了一位哈雷街的医生
I've already consulted a specialist in Harley Street.
他怎么说?
And what does this specialist tell you?
他实在太可笑了
He was preposterous!
竟然认为我无法忍受现在的生活
He asserted my life is so unbearable to me,
才想要自杀
I deliberately want to end it.
他真蠢
He is a fool.
我为什么要自杀?
Why should I want to kill myself?
作为这个国家最富有的人之一
One of the richest men in the country,
我应有尽有
I have everything I could possibly want.
我过得很开心
I am a happy man.
嗯
Mm.
法利先生 现在需要我做什么?
So, where do I come in, M. Farley?
会不会有人想要杀我
Supposing someone wants to kill me.
用这种方式让我死?
Could they do it this way?
您是说用催眠术?
Hypnotism, you mean?
你看到了我现在的处境
You see what I'm getting at.
先生 您觉得谁会想要杀您呢?
Who is it that you suspect of wanting to kill you, monsieur?
没有 我想不到谁想杀我
Nobody, nobody at all.
一个都想不到?
You had no one specific in mind?
当然没有
Certainly not.
啊
Ah.
我想看一看您梦中的场景
I should like to see the scene of this drama --
桌子 钟 手枪
the desk, the clock, the revolver --
不
No.
我已经向你仔细地描述过了
I've told you all there is to tell.
隔壁房间没什么可看的
There's nothing to see next door.
不过 我还是想亲眼看一看
Nevertheless, I should like to see for myself --
没这个必要
There is no need.
我只想听听你怎么看
I just want your opinion.
但是证据太少 我无法给出我的看法
But I can hardly have an opinion on such skimpy evidence.
那就到此为止吧
There's an end of it, then.
能说的我都说了 你却无能为力
I've told you the facts. You can't make anything of it.
这件事就到此为止
That closes the matter.
回去把咨询费账单寄给我
You can send me in your bill for the consultation fee.
我不会忘记寄的
I shall not fail to do so.
等一下
Wait.
那封信 留下来
That letter -- I want it.
您秘书寄给我的信?
The letter from your secretary?
是的
Yes.
啊
Ah.
嗯
Mm.
谢谢
Thank you.
哦 很抱歉 先生
Oh. A thousand pardons, monsieur.
怎么了?
What?
我犯了个愚蠢的错误
I have committed a folly, eh?
刚才给您的那封信
The letter I handed to you just now --
是我房东给我的信
it was a letter from my landlord.
这才是您的那封信
This is your letter.
你怎么这么糊涂
Why the devil can't you watch what you're doing?
啊
Ah.
再见 先生
Au revoir, monsieur.
在上面聊得怎么样?
How'd you get on in there?
啊
Ah.
话不投机
Not well, I'm afraid.
这件事有些不对劲 黑斯廷斯 古怪得很
There is something wrong in that house, Hastings, badly wrong.
可是我却看不出一点端倪
And I haven't the faintest idea what it is.
快去送信
Get off, boy.
这些文件要在下午1点前送到利德贺街
I want these documents in Leadenhall Street by 1:00.
好了 快去吧
Well, go on, then!
快点
Run!
呃 打扰了 先生
Uh, excuse me, sir.
康沃西先生说您愿意抽空谈一谈
Mr. Cornworthy said you might spare us a moment.
嗯?
Hmm?
这是怎么回事?
What's going on?
不是说好12点的么?
12:00, he said.
是 是
All right, all right.
法利先生太忙了
He's a very busy man.
我们坐下再等等
Now, let's just sit down.
别着急
And relax.
康沃西先生
Mr. Cornworthy.
特伦姆莱特先生 您怎么还在这?
Mr. Tremlett, are you still here?
我们在这等了快一个小时了
We've been here an hour, nearly.
一个多小时
Over an hour.
我去看看法利先生在忙什么
Well, I'll go and see what he's up to.
正好这些文件需要他签字
He's got to sign these, anyway.
真急死人了
Bloody nerve.
没时间吃饭 我早料到了
That's our dinner hour gone. I know that.
就快见到他了
He'll see us now.
天啊
Good God!
看在上帝的份上
For God's sake, someone...
快去报警
send for the police!
我真受不了了 波洛先生
I can't go on like this, Mr. Poirot.
那台破打字机已经快把我气疯了
That machine is more than flesh and blood can stand.
可是你之前都没有抱怨过
But you have never complained before.
这半年来我一直在抱怨这台机器
I've done nothing but complain for the last six months.
你没有
No.
她确实提过 波洛
It has been mentioned, Poirot.
你俩合起伙来对付我
Kindly do not band together against Poirot.
我没有
I wasn't.
我一直努力让大家过得开心
Do I not do my best to keep us all happy?
我不想要什么开心
I don't want to be happy.
我只想要台新...
I just want to --
我是波洛
Poirot.
啊 贾普总督察 老朋友
Ah, Inspector Japp, my old friend.
我在本尼迪克特·法利的诺斯韦别墅这里
I'm at Northway House, Poirot, Benedict Farley's place.
希望你能过来一趟
I'd like you to come over here if you'd be so kind.
法利先生自杀了
Mr. Farley has shot himself.
这是我听过最荒唐的故事了
Most peculiar story I ever heard.
我从没听过这么荒谬的事
I've never heard such poppycock.
父亲才不会介意这类噩梦
Father had no use for dreams and such rubbish.
可是确实 是他亲口说的
Nevertheless, that is what he told me.
是的 他也跟我说过这个梦
Yes, he -- he mentioned it to me.
这个梦让他心烦意乱
It upset him very much.
我告诉他这只是消化不良
I told him it was indigestion, I'm afraid.
我建议他找斯蒂林弗利特医生看看
I suggested his calling in Dr. Stillingfleet.
他没找过我
He never did.
根据波洛先生所说 法利先生去了哈雷街
From M. Poirot's story, I gather he went to Harley Street.
嗯
Mm.
他曾说他去看了医生
Yes, he told me he consulted a specialist,
有谁知道 他看的是哪位医生么?
but is it known who this specialist was?
我们都不知道他去看过医生
None of us had any idea that he'd consulted anyone.
他也没向您提起过他的梦?
And he never spoke to you about the dream?
没有
No.
您呢 康沃西先生?
And you, M. Cornworthy?
没有 只字未提
No, he said nothing about it at all.
我只是根据他的口述写了一封信给您
I took down a letter to you at his dictation,
但我不知道他找您所为何事
but I have no idea why he wanted to consult you.
我原以为
I thought it might have something to do
是跟公司的事情有关
with some business irregularity.
嗯 明白了
Hmm. I see.
贾普总督察 你能说说
Inspector Japp, can you tell me
发现法利先生死亡的经过吗?
the events leading up to the death of M. Benedict Farley?
法利先生原本答应今天会见
Well, Mr. Farley had agreed to see two representatives
两个工人代表
from the works.
工人们要求成立工会
There was a proposal for forming a union.
只是一部分的人想法
Some hoped.
嗯 没错
Yes, quite so.
快1点的时候
A little before 1:00,
康沃西先生从自己办公室出来
Mr. Cornworthy here came out of his room
进了法利先生的书房
and went in to Mr. Farley.
最开始他没看到法利先生 以为他不在
He couldn't see him at first and thought the room was empty.
然后他在桌子旁边
Then he caught sight of a boot sticking out
看到了法利先生的脚
from behind the desk.
接下来呢?
And what happened then?
我冲了出去
I ran out of the room,
让管家去叫斯蒂林弗利特医生
and I told the butler to call Dr. Stillingfleet.
管家按我说的做了
And... he did.
尸体当时就在那里
The body was found down there.
谢谢
Thank you.
法利先生是什么时候死的?
At what time did he die, Doctor?
我1点32分对尸体进行了检查
I examined the body at 32 minutes past 1:00.
当时法利先生已经死亡一个多小时了
Mr. Farley had been dead at least one hour.
那么他可能就是在他说的12点28分死的
So, he could have died at this 12:28 he told you about.
没错
Precisely.
手枪上有其它的指纹么?
Were there any fingerprints on the revolver?
只有他自己的
Only his own.
跟我说说这把枪
And please tell me about the revolver itself.
这把枪他一直放在抽屉里
Well, it was the one he kept in the drawer of his desk,
就像他跟你说的一样
again, just as he told you.
法利夫人一眼就认出了这把枪
Mrs. Farley has identified it positively.
明白
I see.
另外 那扇门是这间屋子唯一的入口
What's more, that's the only entrance to the room.
当然除了窗户以外
Well, apart from the windows, I suppose.
估计没人能从窗户爬进来
I cannot see how anybody could climb up there.
一个有钱人选这样的房间作为书房
It's a funny room for a rich man to choose as his study,
实在可笑
isn't it,
从这里只能看到对面的大白墙
with that great ugly blank wall right outside?
我觉得那面墙对法利先生很重要
I think it is important, that wall.
从心理学角度?
You mean psychologically?
有可能
Perhaps.
"12点28分
At 28 minutes past 12:00,
我拉开写字台右手第二个抽屉
I open the second drawer down on the right of my desk.
拿出手枪 装上子弹
I take out a revolver... load it.
走到窗前
I go over to the window.
接下来
And then?
接下来扣动了扳机
And then I shoot myself.
举起枪
I just lift the gun to my head...
扣下扳机"
and shoot myself.
我看不出
I should not have thought
有任何理由去怀疑
that there is any reason for you to doubt
那个梦的准确性 总督察
the accuracy of the dream's prediction, Inspector.
事实上 所有的证据都表明
In fact, there is every reason to suggest
本尼迪克特·法利是自杀
that Benedict Farley committed suicide.
这本应该是毫无疑问的
Well, there would have been no doubt about it at all,
但是我们忽略了一点
but for one point.
哪一点?
And what was that?
写给你的那封信
The letter written to you.
啊 是的
Ah, I see.
这么说赫尔克里·波洛
So, where Hercule Poirot is concerned,
总是与谋杀案如影随形?
there arises immediately the suspicion of murder?
是的
Precisely.
击中
Touché.
您好 波洛先生
Hello, M. Poirot.
您也想来试一试?
Fancy your chances?
不 不 不
Ah, no, no, no, no, no.
非常感谢 小姐
Thank you very much, mademoiselle,
波洛天生是个好静的人
but essentially Hercule Poirot is, uh, a man of peace.
我可以问您几个问题么?
But perhaps, though, I could ask you a few questions.
问吧
Ask away.
您知道令尊在写字台里放了一把枪么?
Did you know that your father kept a revolver in his desk?
不知道
No.
嗯
Ah.
事发当时您和您母亲在哪?
Where were you and your mother -- Ah, pardon.
我是说 您的继母
That is to say, your stepmother --
我没说错吧
That is correct?
是的 露易丝是我父亲第二任妻子
Yes, Louise is my father's second wife.
她只比我大八岁
She's only eight years older than I am.
上周四的晚上 你们在哪?
So, where were you and she on Thursday night of last week?
上周四...
Thursday.
我们去看戏了 看的是《大拇指》
We went to the theater to see "Thumbs Up."
您父亲没提出一块儿去么?
And your father did not suggest accompanying you?
他从来不看戏的
He never went out to theaters.
他不太喜欢交际?
He was not a very sociable man?
我父亲是个异常孤僻的人
My father had a singularly unpleasant personality.
您很直言不讳
That is a very candid statement, mademoiselle.
波洛先生 我在节省您的时间
I'm saving you time, M. Poirot.
我知道您的意思
I realize quite well what you're getting at.
我住在这儿 是因为我没钱住其它地方
I live here because I have no money to live elsewhere.
我很喜欢一个人 想要嫁给他 但是他很穷
There is a man that I wish to marry -- a poor man.
我父亲干预了我们的事 让他没了工作
My father saw to it that he lost his job.
父亲想让我嫁个有钱人
He wanted me, you see, to marry well --
因为我是他的继承人
an easy matter since I was his heiress.
这么说 您继承了令尊的财产?
So, your father's fortune passes to you?
是的
Yes.
他留给露易丝 我的继母
Well, that is to say, he left Louise, my stepmother,
25万英镑 免税的
£250, 000 free of tax,
还有其它一小部分东西
and there are other few small legacies,
其余的都留给我了
but the residue of it goes to me.
所以 波洛先生
So, you see, M. Poirot,
我没有理由不希望父亲死掉
I had every reason to desire my father's death.
我还看出 小姐
I see, also, mademoiselle,
您也继承了令尊的聪明才智
that you have inherited your father's intelligence.
父亲是很聪明
Father was clever.
但这一切都变成了痛苦
But yet it all turned sour.
没有什么爱与关怀了
There was no humanity left.
还有什么要问的么?
Is there anything more?
有的
Yes.
令尊的视力很差么?
How poor was your father's eyesight?
他不戴眼镜基本上什么都看不到
He could scarcely see at all, and not without his glasses.
小时候他视力就很差
His sight had always been bad, from a boy.
戴上眼镜之后呢?
But with his glasses?
哦 那就没什么问题了
Oh, he could see all right then, of course.
谢谢
Thank you.
好了 警员 去告诉波尔巡佐
All right, Constable, tell Sergeant Ball
比预想的要长一些
this is gonna take longer than expected.
好的 长官
Right, sir.
啊 法利夫人
Ah, Mrs. Farley.
我想问您几个问题
There's something I'd like to ask you.
请说
Yes?
您丈夫被催眠过么?
Had your husband ever been hypnotized?
据我所知没有
Never, to my knowledge.
那他对催眠术感兴趣么?
Was he interested in that sort of thing -- hypnotism?
不
No.
哦 那个可怕的梦
Oh, that horrible dream.
真是太离奇了 每晚都是同样的梦
It's uncanny, to dream that same awful dream, night after night.
就像一直被死神追赶着
It's as though he were hounded to his death.
在您的印象中
Had it ever occurred to you
法利先生有过自杀的倾向么?
that your husband might be tempted to do away with himself?
没有
No.
有时候他确实很奇怪
Well, sometimes he -- he was rather queer.
胡说
Poppycock.
父亲一向爱惜自己 他不会自杀的
Father was far too fond of himself ever to commit suicide.
有些事你不知道 乔安娜
You don't know everything, Joanna.
我什么都知道
I know that much.
请问 法利夫人
Pardon, Mme. Farley.
您丈夫有几副眼镜?
How many pairs of glasses did your husband own?
眼镜?
Glasses?
嗯 是的 眼镜
Uh, well, spectacles.
我不太清楚 三四副吧
I have no idea -- three, four?
啊
Ah.
嗯 谢谢
Hmm. Thank you.
请进
Come in.
天啊 这间屋子白天看起来大不一样
Ah, mon Dieu, how different this room looks in daylight.
有什么可以效劳的?
Can I do something for you?
先生 我发现
Ah, and I see, monsieur,
您和您已故的老板在办公室能看到的风景
that you share the same inspiring view
是一样的
as your late employer.
是的
Oh, yes.
那面墙里边
On the other side of that wall
是为法利先生干活的工人们
are the fools who made Mr. Farley's wealth for him.
我觉得这也是为什么他选择
I think that's why he chose to have his study
这一侧的房间当书房
this side of the house.
明白了
I see.
如果这墙能说话 它肯定能
You know, I feel sure, if that wall could talk,
告诉我们些什么
it would tell us something, no?
嗯
Mm.
康沃西先生 上周四晚上我来的时候
M. Cornworthy, when I arrived last Thursday evening,
法利先生没把我带去自己的房间
I was not shown into M. Farley's own room.
是的
No.
法利先生说让管家带您来这儿
I was told to tell Holmes to show you in here.
您想过为什么吗?
Why was that, do you think?
对法利先生的命令我从来不问为什么
I never questioned any of Mr. Farley's orders.
是 是 是
No, no, no, no.
他经常在您这儿会客么?
Did he usually receive the visitors in here?
经常的
Quite often...
尤其是以前没来过的客人
particularly if people hadn't come to the house before.
明白了
I see. Mm.
谢谢 康沃西先生
Thank you, M. Cornworthy.
总督察 本尼迪克特·法利的这个梦
Inspector, this dream of Benedict Farley
至关重要
is very important.
他说他梦到自己自杀了
He dreamed, he said, of committing suicide.
然后 他真的自杀了
And later on, he did commit suicide.
这起"自杀"
Now, when I say "suicide,"
他是一个人在房间里
he was alone in his room
被发现的时候手里拿着枪
and was found with a gun in his hand.
而且在他开枪的时候没有人进出过
And no one entered or left the room at the time he was shot.
这说明了什么 总督察?
So, what does this mean, Chief Inspector?
说明没有其他可能
Well, that there's no other possibility --
一定是自杀
that it must be suicide.
恰恰相反
Au contraire.
说明这是一起非同寻常的
It means a very unusual
精心策划的谋杀
and very cleverly planned murder.
怎么做到的? 谁策划的?
Planned how? Planned by who?
总督察 要是我直接说出答案
Well, it is no good, is it, Chief Inspector,
恐怕不太好吧
if I just give you the answer?
嗯
Well --
是的
No.
得多给灰色小细胞些时间搞清楚过程
We must give the little gray cells time to do their work, eh?
也多给波洛一点时间查出事情真相
And give Poirot time to work out who did it and how.
波洛 这可不大像你
This is not like you, Poirot.
好吧 黑斯廷斯 这也不像我的灰色小细胞
Well, this is not like the gray cells, Hastings!
我尽了一切努力
I have given them every chance.
宠爱着它们
They have been cosseted.
我保持睡眠充足
I have slept to allow them to do their work.
我早餐吃鱼肉
I have eaten fish for breakfast.
可结果呢? 还是不行
Result -- nothing!
会有结果的 波洛
It'll come, Poirot.
你的灰色小细胞从来没让你失望过
The little gray cells have never let you down yet.
啊
Ah.
但这也许是活力减退的信号
But is this not an indication, perhaps, of what is in store?
是因为我年纪太大还是生活节奏太快?
A sign that they are weakened by old age and the fast living?
节奏太快?
Fast living, Poirot?
我可没看出来
I wouldn't call your life exactly fast.
嗯 现在也许不快了 我指年轻时候
Well, not now, perhaps, Hastings, but... in my youth.
真的?
Really?
哦
Oh.
真的?
Really?
是的 黑斯廷斯
You see, one pays, Hastings.
年轻时用脑过度 现在脑子不灵了
Eventually, one is called to settle one's account.
这样啊
I say.
哦
Oh.
我得再来杯茶
I shall have another tisane.
真是疯了
Bother!
波洛先生 我...
Mr. Poirot, I --
怎么了 波洛先生?
What is it, Mr. Poirot?
请再来一杯茶 莱蒙小姐
Another tisane, if you please, Miss Lemon.
哦 天啊
Oh, dear.
你9点钟刚喝过
You had your 9:00 one.
动脑子需要这茶 莱蒙小姐
Well, serious measures are called for, Miss Lemon.
见鬼
Mon Dieu.
莱蒙小姐 能告诉我现在几点了么?
Do you have the time, please, Miss Lemon?
当然 波洛先生
Of course, Mr. Poirot.
嗯
Ah.
你在做什么 莱蒙小姐?
What are you doing, Miss Lemon?
9点55分了 波洛先生
It's 5 to 10:00, Mr. Poirot.
你为什么往窗外看?
But what were you doing out there?
我探出身去 就能看到教堂的钟了
If I lean right out, I can just see the church clock.
戴块表岂不是更方便?
But would it not be simpler to wear the watch?
不行 波洛先生
I can't, M. Poirot.
我的磁场干扰手表
My magnetism upsets them.
明白了
I say.
什么样的手表我戴都走不准
All my life, I've been looking for a watch that won't go wild
没找到一块能走好的
as soon as I put it on, but I've never met it.
你到底怎么了 波洛先生?
What ever is the matter, Mr. Poirot?
莱蒙小姐 你真是太漂亮了
Miss Lemon, you are beautiful.
麻烦你
Now, would you please be so kind
打个电话给贾普总督察
as to telephone the Chief Inspector Japp
让他中午把法利全家人都召集到
and ask him to assemble the whole Farley household at noon?
大厅里
In the hall, hein?
来吧 黑斯廷斯 我们有事做了
Come, Hastings. We have work to do.
案子要水落石出了
All has become clear.
工人们把馅饼从面粉车间运送到这
Then they're brought in here from the pastry room
放进烤炉
and loaded into the ovens.
炉子一般得在12点15分前关闭
The ovens have got to be sealed and closed by 12:15
12点30分馅饼准时开始烘烤
because we start the bake at 12:30 sharp.
如果没有准时开炉
If we hadn't done that,
在你还没反应过来时
Mr. Farley was on the telephone
法利先生的电话就会打过来
quicker than you can say "three little piggies."
他定期来车间里吗?
Did he come regularly to the factory?
哦 不
Oh, no.
这六七年间
No, he hadn't done that
他都没有定期来工厂
for, uh -- oh, six or seven years.
他不常来
Well, not regularly,
但总知道我们没有按时开炉
but he seemed to know if we hadn't started the bake on time.
我们常说只要是跟馅饼有关
In the office, we used to say he had second sight
他就长了透视眼吧
as far as a pork pie was concerned.
当然这只是个笑话
But that was just by way of a joke.
馅饼烘烤
Then after the bake,
大约需要一个半小时
which takes about an hour and half,
然后我们把它们拿出来
we take them out of the ovens,
绕过那个转角...
and then they go around the corner...
照我跟你说的做
Now, remember what I told you.
好的
Yes.
装子弹了么?
Is it loaded?
哦 是的
Oh, yes.
他来了
Here he comes.
大家好
Bonjour.
我想知道 这个案件里最特别的地方
I wonder -- what is the most extraordinary thing
是什么呢?
about this case, hmm?
我认为 是那个梦吧
Well, the dream, I'd say.
如果我们没从你那儿听说的话 波洛
If we hadn't got your word for it, Poirot --
确实如此 对那个梦的讲述是关键
Exactement. The telling of the dream was vital.
但是 比梦更重要的是
But, mes amis, there is more to it than that.
法利先生是在哪里讲述他的梦的
Where did this telling of the dream take place?
法利先生当时在他秘书这里接待的我
M. Benedict Farley received me here in his secretary's room
并且断然拒绝带我去他自己的书房
and refused, point-blank, to let me see into his own room,
虽然就差那么几步
just a few feet away.
他为什么不带我去呢?
Why did he do that, hein?
因为那间房里
Because there was something in that room
有不想让我看到的东西
he could not afford to have me see.
什么东西?
What?
我们稍后会说到的
We will come to that.
当法利先生让我把邀请信还给他的时候
When M. Benedict Farley asked me to return his letter to him,
我稀里糊涂拿了房东给我的信
by inadvertence, I handed to him the correspondence
交给了他
from my landlord.
他本该一眼就看出来给错了
One glance should have told him it was a wrong letter.
他当时戴眼镜了么?
Didn't he have his glasses on?
是的 他还戴着眼镜
Oh, yes, he had on his glasses.
那为什么法利先生没分辨出
So, why did M. Benedict Farley not realize the difference
两封差别如此大的信呢?
between two totally dissimilar letters, hein?
我的朋友们 这是因为
Because, mes amis,
当时跟我在一起的那个人并不近视
I was in the company of a man with normal eyesight
却戴了一副高度数眼镜
wearing powerful glasses.
度数这么高的眼镜
And such powerful glasses
视力正常的人戴了就跟瞎子一样
would render a man of normal eyesight practically blind.
是这样吧 医生?
Is that not so, Doctor?
度数足够高的话 是这样
If they were very powerful spectacles, yes.
这就对了
Eh bien!
回到刚才的问题
So, why was I not allowed to go
为什么不让我进法利先生的房间?
into M. Benedict Farley's room that night?
那里到底有什么
What was in M. Benedict Farley's room
是不能让我看见的?
that I was not allowed to see?
女士们 先生们 让我来告诉大家
Mesdames et messieurs, shall I enlighten you?
希望你知道 波洛
I wish you would, Poirot.
那好吧
Very well.
让波洛来告诉大家
Poirot shall enlighten you.
在法利先生的房间里
What was in M. Benedict Farley's own room
不能让我看到的
that M. Benedict Farley did not allow me to see was...
是真正的法利先生
M. Benedict Farley.
天啊
Good God.
昨天下午
Yesterday afternoon,
有三个人可以出面证实
there are three witnesses to swear
没有人出入过法利先生的房间
that no one comes in or out of M. Benedict Farley's room.
康沃西先生就在隔壁他自己的办公室里
M. Cornworthy is in his room next door,
12点28时 他做好了准备
and as 12:28 approaches, he readies himself.
你们看 康沃西先生知道很多
You see, M. Cornworthy knows something
多数人不知道的秘密
that very few other people know, hmm?
他知道 这么多年来
He knows that M. Benedict Farley, every day,
法利先生每天
after all these years,
仍然沉醉于
still interested
对工厂的日常管理
in the day-to-day running of his factory,
监督他的工人
checks up on his employees.
我们来看看他是怎么做的
Let us see how he does this.
这位馅饼大王是怎么足不出户
How can this king of pies observe his workers
监视工厂里的一切的?
without ever leaving this house, hein?
很简单
Simple.
我们大家都知道
You see, the uninviting delicacy
馅饼在烘烤之前需要先蒸一个小时
is first steamed for one hour before it is baked,
只要馅饼一进炉
and the release valves on the vast ovens,
墙对面那边的放气阀
which are situated beyond that wall,
就会放出大量的蒸汽来
are briefly tested as soon as the ovens are loaded.
嗯
Mm.
好的
Eh bien.
如果你从窗户探出身去
If one leans out of this window,
就很容易看到
one can readily confirm this fact.
现在 请大家
Now, if you please,
都到窗前来 探出身去
I want you all to come to these two windows, lean out,
向右看
and look to your right.
康沃西先生 不如您先来
M. Cornworthy, why don't you lead the way, hmm?
您是在胡说八道
Oh, this is nonsense.
也许吧
Perhaps.
就当迁就我一下
But humor me?
谢谢
Merci.
大家都来吧
Alors, viens, viens, viens.
法利夫人?
Mme. Farley?
哦 好吧
Oh, very well.
现在大家都能看到
Now, one can readily see
蒸汽从烟囱或者楼东边的
that spurt of steam issuing from the chimney or pipe
管子里喷出来
at the eastern end of the building. Voilà?
我还是弄不明白
All the same, I don't see where that gets us.
法利先生走到窗前
M. Farley comes to the window.
然后呢?
Yes?
他探出身去看放气阀 以确定准时开炉
He leans out to make sure that the bake is starting on time.
好的
All right.
接下来
And then...
康沃西先生开枪 法利先生中枪倒地
M. Cornworthy shoots him, and Farley falls to the floor.
记得吗? 对面有一面白墙
Remember -- there is a blank wall opposite,
所以没有任何目击者
so there can be no witnesses.
一派胡言
Lies, ridiculous lies.
一切都是显而易见的 对吧?
All has the appearance of being above the board, yes?
特伦姆莱特先生等人仅仅
M. Tremlett and the other men
看到康沃西先生走进法利先生的房间
see M. Cornworthy go into M. Farley's room,
然后很快冲了出来
but rush out again
大叫法利先生死了
with the announcement of M. Farley's suicide.
当然 他们没有看到
What they do not, of course, see
康沃西先生把枪放进死者的手里
is M. Cornworthy press the gun into M. Farley's hand.
您这是恶意中伤
Slanderous rubbish.
那封邀请信其实是康沃西先生写给我的
It was M. Cornworthy who wrote to me the letter,
也是康沃西先生给了管家那些指示
M. Cornworthy who gave instructions to the butler.
并且在房间化了妆
It was he who went up to his bedroom, applied the makeup,
伪装成本尼迪克特·法利先生
and played the part of Benedict Farley.
实际上是两个人策划了整个事件
But there were two people who carried through this fraud.
除了康沃西先生之外
M. Cornworthy was one,
另一个人是...
and the other...
法利夫人
Mme. Farley.
你怎么敢这么说?
How dare you?!
本应该有个幸福美满的结局
In due course, the happy ending would have been achieved.
25万英镑和两颗跳动如一的心
£250,000, and two hearts that beat as one.
黑斯廷斯 拦住他
Hastings, stop him!
哦
Ohh!
拦住他 赫伯特 拦住他
Stop him, Herbert! Stop him!
什么?
What?
哦 好的
Oh. Right.
停下
I say!
干得好 年轻人
Well done, sir!
那是赫伯特
That's Herbert.
我是来带你私奔的 你会跟我走吧?
I've come to elope. It's still on, is it?
不用了 我们不用私奔了
It's not, strictly speaking, necessary anymore.
哦
Oh.
如果你喜欢 我们还是可以私奔
Well, we could do it, anyway, though, if you like.
好的
Yes.
该拿他怎么办?
What shall I do with him?
把他交给我吧 先生 非常感谢
I'll deal with him, sir. Thank you very much.
再见 法利夫人
Au revoir, Mme. Farley.
你这个外国佬
You foreigner.
下午好 先生
Good afternoon, sir.
下午好
Good afternoon.
我帮您拿吧
Can I assist you in any way, sir?
-谢谢  -不客气
-Thank you. -Thank you.
-谢谢  -谢谢
-您拿好  -谢谢
-Thank you. -Thank you.
我来拿吧
Can I give you a breather with that?
不 不 谢谢你 黑斯廷斯
No, no, no, no. Thank you, Hastings.
我还能坚持这最后几步
I'm sure I can manage the last five paces.
波洛先生 我来吧
Mr. Poirot, let me help you.
不 不 不 莱蒙小姐
No, no, no, no, no, no, Miss Lemon.
这是给你的
This is for you.
哦 波洛先生 您太客气了
Oh, Mr. Poirot, you shouldn't have.
不 不 不 这没什么的
No, no, no, no, no, no, nonsense, Miss Lemon.
黑斯廷斯 麻烦拿把刀来
Hastings, if you please -- the knife.
谢谢
Merci.
现在... 请看
Et maintenant... voilà!
莱蒙小姐 你觉得怎么样?
Well, what do you think, eh, Miss Lemon?
-这...  -太棒了 是吧?
-It's -- -Wonderful, eh?
这...
It's --
现在我们就不用
Now we shall have...
危险地探出身子到窗外
no more leaning dangerously out of the window
去看时间了
to tell the time, yes?
这正是我想要的
It's just what I wanted.
黑斯廷斯 有两个原因
Hastings... there are two reasons
我不能成为百万富翁
why I should never become the millionaire.
是什么原因?
What are they, Poirot?
第一个
The first --
我不会做那些难吃的馅饼
that I should never make the detestable pork pies, hein?
第二个
And the second.
我实在太理解我的员工了
I am too understanding towards my employees.
是吧
Quite.